<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Bates Fluid Dynamics Group</title>
    <link>https://jsoishi.github.io/</link>
    <description>Recent content on Bates Fluid Dynamics Group</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <copyright>&amp;copy; Jeffrey S. Oishi, 2018-present; banner image NASA/SWRI/MSSS/Gerald Eichstädt/Seán Doran</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Sat, 01 Jul 2023 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="https://jsoishi.github.io/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Minimal Models of Moist Convection</title>
      <link>https://jsoishi.github.io/project/moistconvection/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 01 Jul 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://jsoishi.github.io/project/moistconvection/</guid>
      <description>Motivation When water vapor condenses in the atmosphere, it releases latent heat and changes the buoyancy of the surrounding air. This phase transition is a fundamentally non-linear process that dramatically shapes the evolution of convection, making it fundamentally different than ``dry&amp;rsquo;&amp;rsquo; convection without moisture. Convective activity plays a key role in the climate system, including the radiation inhibition driven by clouds and the formation of severe weather. Today&amp;rsquo;s most advanced global climate models do not reliably resolve the formation of clouds, and thus they include significant model-dependent details that drive disagreements in the results.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Ordering of timescales predicts applicability of quasi-linear theory in unstable flows</title>
      <link>https://jsoishi.github.io/publication/2023arxiv230703781s/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 01 Jul 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://jsoishi.github.io/publication/2023arxiv230703781s/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The photometric variability of massive stars due to gravity waves excited by core convection</title>
      <link>https://jsoishi.github.io/publication/2023arxiv230608023a/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 01 Jun 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://jsoishi.github.io/publication/2023arxiv230608023a/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The Puzzling Structure of Solar Convection: Window into the Dynamo</title>
      <link>https://jsoishi.github.io/publication/2023arxiv230508823f/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 May 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://jsoishi.github.io/publication/2023arxiv230508823f/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Generalized quasi-linear approximation and non-normality in Taylor-Couette spiral turbulence</title>
      <link>https://jsoishi.github.io/publication/2023rspta.38120122o/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 01 Mar 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://jsoishi.github.io/publication/2023rspta.38120122o/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Well, that&#39;s a relief</title>
      <link>https://jsoishi.github.io/post/agreement/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 13 Jan 2023 00:44:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://jsoishi.github.io/post/agreement/</guid>
      <description>We released the beta version of Dedalus version 3 just under a year ago, on 15 Feb 2022. In that time, we&amp;rsquo;ve made tremendous progress in performance, usability, and IO. One thing that&amp;rsquo;s always gratifying is when you port a script as closely as you can, by copying and pasting and modifying until it conforms to the new syntax and find this:
And for the one run I checked, Dedalus 3 is 2.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The stability of Prendergast magnetic fields</title>
      <link>https://jsoishi.github.io/publication/2022mnras.517.3332k/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 01 Dec 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://jsoishi.github.io/publication/2022mnras.517.3332k/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Sometimes you can&#39;t let the mystery be</title>
      <link>https://jsoishi.github.io/post/welcome-to-brown/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 06 Oct 2022 17:23:48 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://jsoishi.github.io/post/welcome-to-brown/</guid>
      <description>&amp;hellip;or how six months in the lab can save you an hour in the library.
For the 2022-2023 year, I&amp;rsquo;m visiting the Brown Theoretical Physics Center, hosted by Brad Marston. I&amp;rsquo;m excited to chat with all of the great fluid dynamicists here and hopefully start some new lines of research.
In fact, that&amp;rsquo;s already happened. In my second week at Brown, who comes to visit? None other than Professor Alexander Morozov from the University of Edinburgh, one of the world&amp;rsquo;s foremost experts on elastic turbulence, and a keen user of Dedalus.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Direct Statistical Simulation of the Busse Annulus</title>
      <link>https://jsoishi.github.io/publication/2022arxiv220303699o/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 01 Oct 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://jsoishi.github.io/publication/2022arxiv220303699o/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Experiment Sees Elusive Magnetic-Fluid Instability</title>
      <link>https://jsoishi.github.io/publication/2022phyoj..15..134o/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 01 Sep 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://jsoishi.github.io/publication/2022phyoj..15..134o/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The Stability of Prendergast Magnetic Fields</title>
      <link>https://jsoishi.github.io/publication/2022arxiv220914339k/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 01 Sep 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://jsoishi.github.io/publication/2022arxiv220914339k/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Convective Boundary Mixing Processes</title>
      <link>https://jsoishi.github.io/publication/2022rnaas...6...41a/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 01 Feb 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://jsoishi.github.io/publication/2022rnaas...6...41a/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Theses, Papers, and other things.</title>
      <link>https://jsoishi.github.io/post/summer-2021/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 30 Jun 2021 15:41:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://jsoishi.github.io/post/summer-2021/</guid>
      <description>First off, a hearty congratulations to Xiaole &amp;ldquo;Alex&amp;rdquo; Jiang (Bates &amp;lsquo;21) and Kirstin Koepnick (Bates &amp;lsquo;21) for successfully defending their Honors Theses! Alex&amp;rsquo;s work concerned non-linear wave generation in rapidly rotating convection while Kirstin began an investigation of the smallest topologically protected system in classical mechanics.
While we&amp;rsquo;re congratulating, a very belated congrats to Morgan Baxter (Bates &amp;lsquo;20), who defended the very first Honors Thesis to come out of the Bates Fluids Group.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>eigentools: A Python package for studying differential eigenvalue problems with an emphasis on robustness</title>
      <link>https://jsoishi.github.io/publication/2021joss....6.3079o/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 01 Jun 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://jsoishi.github.io/publication/2021joss....6.3079o/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The Pencil Code, a modular MPI code for partial differential equations and particles: multipurpose and multiuser-maintained</title>
      <link>https://jsoishi.github.io/publication/2021joss....6.2807p/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Feb 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://jsoishi.github.io/publication/2021joss....6.2807p/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Tucker Barber</title>
      <link>https://jsoishi.github.io/member/tbarber/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 12 Jan 2021 15:52:22 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://jsoishi.github.io/member/tbarber/</guid>
      <description>Tucker wrote his senior thesis on testing the forthcoming Dedalus-bio software package for biophysics simulations.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Reduced Models: GQL, DSS, and anisotropic flows</title>
      <link>https://jsoishi.github.io/project/reducedmodels/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 01 Dec 2020 16:10:22 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://jsoishi.github.io/project/reducedmodels/</guid>
      <description>Turbulence is a crucial part of the climate, the dynamo process by which the Sun and Earth produce magnetic fields, and a major limiting factor for plasma confinement in tokamaks. In each of these systems, the largest scales are factors of 105 to 1014 times larger than the smallest scales. Crucially, energy flows through all of these scales, impacting the dynamics of the flow. A complete numerical simulation would require between 1015 to 1042 data points for every moment in time simulated!</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Single-hemisphere Dynamos in M-dwarf Stars</title>
      <link>https://jsoishi.github.io/publication/2020apj...902l...3b/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 01 Oct 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://jsoishi.github.io/publication/2020apj...902l...3b/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Dedalus: A flexible framework for numerical simulations with spectral methods</title>
      <link>https://jsoishi.github.io/publication/2020phrvr...2b3068b/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 01 Apr 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://jsoishi.github.io/publication/2020phrvr...2b3068b/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The magnetorotational instability prefers three dimensions</title>
      <link>https://jsoishi.github.io/publication/2020rspsa.47690622o/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 31 Jan 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://jsoishi.github.io/publication/2020rspsa.47690622o/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Welcome new members!</title>
      <link>https://jsoishi.github.io/post/winter-2020/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 23 Jan 2020 15:41:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://jsoishi.github.io/post/winter-2020/</guid>
      <description>As we start the winter term, we welcome two new members to our ranks. First, Anthony Okonkwo (Bates &amp;lsquo;20) joins the group as a senior thesis student working on fluid-structure interaction and modelling Taylor&amp;rsquo;s swimming sheet using immersed boundary methods in Dedalus. Anthony is majoring in physics and engineering and is particularly interested in mechanical engineering. Second, Muhammad Abdullah (Bates &amp;lsquo;22) is joining the group as a research student. He&amp;rsquo;s just getting started on instability theory, with an eye on helping to design a Goldreich-Schubert-Fricke lab experiment.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Performance of parallel-in-time integration for Rayleigh Bénard Convection</title>
      <link>https://jsoishi.github.io/publication/2020arxiv200101609c/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 01 Jan 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://jsoishi.github.io/publication/2020arxiv200101609c/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>A busy semester winds down</title>
      <link>https://jsoishi.github.io/post/three-new-papers/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 03 Dec 2019 15:54:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://jsoishi.github.io/post/three-new-papers/</guid>
      <description>The snow is falling, the semester is winding down, and everyone&amp;rsquo;s looking forward to a break. It&amp;rsquo;s been a very busy year for the Bates Fluids group, and I&amp;rsquo;m excited to announce that in the past few weeks, we&amp;rsquo;ve had three (!!) papers accepted, including one featuring group member Morgan Baxter (Bates &amp;lsquo;20). The vast range of topics these papers cover, from biofilm growth to the stability of rotating plasmas to the flexible numerical methods we work on, speaks to the extremely broad applicability of fluid dynamics!</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Flow-Induced Symmetry Breaking in Growing Bacterial Biofilms</title>
      <link>https://jsoishi.github.io/publication/2019phrvl.123y8101p/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 01 Dec 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://jsoishi.github.io/publication/2019phrvl.123y8101p/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>ENZO: An Adaptive Mesh Refinement Code for Astrophysics (Version 2.6)</title>
      <link>https://jsoishi.github.io/publication/2019joss....4.1636b/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 01 Oct 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://jsoishi.github.io/publication/2019joss....4.1636b/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Papers published!</title>
      <link>https://jsoishi.github.io/post/spheres-papers/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 29 Sep 2019 15:01:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://jsoishi.github.io/post/spheres-papers/</guid>
      <description>I&amp;rsquo;m excited to annouce that our two papers on spin-weighted spherical harmonics are finally published in the Journal of Computational Physics X. The first paper covers the mathematical formalism, while the second paper demonstrates its performance in a number of test problems, including a fully convective, rotating dynamo problem:
On the right is the radial velocity while the left shows magnetic field lines, visualized using Vapor.
The most significant part of this research, aside from the fact that we have sparse, efficient spectrally accurate spherical basis functions in Dedalus, is that by using spin-weighted spherical harmonics, one can implement equations on the sphere directly in vector form:</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Welcome back!</title>
      <link>https://jsoishi.github.io/post/new-year-2019-2020/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 14 Sep 2019 15:01:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://jsoishi.github.io/post/new-year-2019-2020/</guid>
      <description>It&amp;rsquo;s the start of a new year, and we have several new members in the group. Welcome to senior thesis students Fahim Khan and Avi Brach-Neufeld, juniors Hannah Beams, Becca Minsley, and Alex Jiang! Morgan Baxter is returning from a successful summer project to start his senior thesis as well.
Fahim is going to be focusing on some interesting infrastructure, trying to figure out how to streamline the management of supercomputer simulations.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Dedalus Tutorials</title>
      <link>https://jsoishi.github.io/research/dedalus_tutorials/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 17 Jul 2019 08:50:58 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://jsoishi.github.io/research/dedalus_tutorials/</guid>
      <description>Double Diffusive Convection In order to run this, you can find the code at Github.
First, we have the so-called &amp;ldquo;fingering&amp;rdquo; regime of DDC, which you can run with this script   
Next, we have &amp;ldquo;overstable&amp;rdquo; DDC, which you can run with this script</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Breezing through the Space Environment of Barnard’s Star b</title>
      <link>https://jsoishi.github.io/publication/2019apj...875l..12a/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Apr 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://jsoishi.github.io/publication/2019apj...875l..12a/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Tensor calculus in spherical coordinates using Jacobi polynomials, Part-II: Implementation and Examples</title>
      <link>https://jsoishi.github.io/publication/2018arxiv180409283l/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 01 Mar 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://jsoishi.github.io/publication/2018arxiv180409283l/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Tensor calculus in spherical coordinates using Jacobi polynomials. Part-I: Mathematical analysis and derivations</title>
      <link>https://jsoishi.github.io/publication/2018arxiv180410320v/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 01 Mar 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://jsoishi.github.io/publication/2018arxiv180410320v/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The &#34;Sphered Cube&#34;: A New Method for the Solution of Partial Differential Equations in Cubical Geometry</title>
      <link>https://jsoishi.github.io/publication/2019arxiv190312642b/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 01 Mar 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://jsoishi.github.io/publication/2019arxiv190312642b/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Predicting the Rossby Number in Convective Experiments</title>
      <link>https://jsoishi.github.io/publication/2019apj...872..138a/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 01 Feb 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://jsoishi.github.io/publication/2019apj...872..138a/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>GQL Busse Annulus paper published</title>
      <link>https://jsoishi.github.io/post/gql-busse-paper/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 05 Dec 2018 17:23:48 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://jsoishi.github.io/post/gql-busse-paper/</guid>
      <description>Our paper on the Generalized Quasi-linear Approximation for the Busse Annulus problem was published in Proceedings of the Royal Society A!</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Guide to Getting Started </title>
      <link>https://jsoishi.github.io/research/getting_started/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 22 Nov 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://jsoishi.github.io/research/getting_started/</guid>
      <description>Welcome to the Bates Fluid Dynamics Group! Most of our work involves solving partial differential equations by computer. Typically, this means running simulations on supercomputers, most often the Leavitt cluster here at Bates.
Using Linux  All of the group&amp;rsquo;s software runs on Linux. You need to be familiar with the command line, and it helps to know a bit of bash shell scripting. We use the git version control system.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Using Leavitt</title>
      <link>https://jsoishi.github.io/research/leavitt/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 22 Nov 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://jsoishi.github.io/research/leavitt/</guid>
      <description>Basics In order to log in to leavitt, you will need to use ssh to connect to leavitt.bates.edu. When you log in to leavitt via ssh, you will be on the &amp;ldquo;head node&amp;rdquo;. This node is identical to the other nodes. It has 28 cores and 128 GB of memory. This machine is for doing small analysis tasks and submitting jobs. DO NOT RUN DEDALUS ON THE HEAD NODE. Instead, use a job script to submit runs to the compute nodes.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Generalized quasilinear approximation of the interaction of convection and mean flows in a thermal annulus</title>
      <link>https://jsoishi.github.io/publication/2018rspsa.47480422t/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 01 Nov 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://jsoishi.github.io/publication/2018rspsa.47480422t/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>A Complex Fluids Toolkit for Dedalus</title>
      <link>https://jsoishi.github.io/project/complex_fluids_toolkit/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Oct 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://jsoishi.github.io/project/complex_fluids_toolkit/</guid>
      <description>Motivation Complex fluids, including liquid crystals and those with non-Newtonian rheologies, are extremely important in a wide variety of disciplines, from biological to industrial. We are developing a series of tools to extend the Dedalus to include multiphase flows with varying rheologies.
Methods We make extensive use of the phase field method to simulate two fluids on the same grid. This idea, sometimes also called the &amp;ldquo;diffusive interface model&amp;rdquo;, assumes that we resolve the interface between the two fluids.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Accelerated evolution of convective simulations</title>
      <link>https://jsoishi.github.io/publication/2018phrvf...3h3502a/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 01 Aug 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://jsoishi.github.io/publication/2018phrvf...3h3502a/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Research Overview</title>
      <link>https://jsoishi.github.io/research/overview/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 19 Jul 2018 08:50:58 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://jsoishi.github.io/research/overview/</guid>
      <description>Mission The Bates Fluid Dynamics Group studies fluid and plasma dynamics using theoretical and computational tools. We are interested in problems related to Earth&amp;rsquo;s ocean and atmosphere, the confinement of plasmas in future fusion power generators, the Sun&amp;rsquo;s magnetic field, and Jupiter&amp;rsquo;s atmosphere. We take the physicist&amp;rsquo;s approach to these questions: how can we use simplified models of isolated processes to develop a robust, systematic understanding of the dynamics?
Much of the group&amp;rsquo;s efforts are focused on stability and control of shear flows, particularly as they apply to major environmental and clean energy problems: how can we better model the vertical transport of heat and pollutants in climate models?</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Direct Statistical Simulation for unsteady flows</title>
      <link>https://jsoishi.github.io/project/busseannulus/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 01 May 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://jsoishi.github.io/project/busseannulus/</guid>
      <description>Motivation Direct Statistical Simulation is a relatively new and very promising technique for understanding the long-term statistical properties of highly turbulent, anisotropic flow. Anisotropic flow occurs in astrophysical and geophysical contexts in a number of guises: the zonal jets found on Jupiter and Saturn, the mean dynamo-generated magnetic fields on solar-type and fully convective M-dwarfs, and the quasi-biennial oscillation on Earth. DSS has been extensively verified and tested against many problems in atmospheric science \citep{2008JAtS&amp;hellip;65.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Convective Dynamics and Disequilibrium Chemistry in the Atmospheres of Giant Planets and Brown Dwarfs</title>
      <link>https://jsoishi.github.io/publication/2018apj...854....8b/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 01 Feb 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://jsoishi.github.io/publication/2018apj...854....8b/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Perspectives on Reproducibility and Sustainability of Open-Source Scientific Software from Seven Years of the Dedalus Project</title>
      <link>https://jsoishi.github.io/publication/2018arxiv180108200o/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://jsoishi.github.io/publication/2018arxiv180108200o/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>New website!</title>
      <link>https://jsoishi.github.io/post/post1/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 05 Nov 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://jsoishi.github.io/post/post1/</guid>
      <description>So we built a website!</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The Weakly Nonlinear Magnetorotational Instability in a Global, Cylindrical Taylor-Couette Flow</title>
      <link>https://jsoishi.github.io/publication/2017apj...841....2c/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 May 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://jsoishi.github.io/publication/2017apj...841....2c/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The Weakly Nonlinear Magnetorotational Instability in a Local Geometry</title>
      <link>https://jsoishi.github.io/publication/2017apj...841....1c/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 May 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://jsoishi.github.io/publication/2017apj...841....1c/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Hybrid Adaptive Ray-Moment Method (HARM&lt;SUP&gt;2&lt;/SUP&gt;): A highly parallel method for radiation hydrodynamics on adaptive grids</title>
      <link>https://jsoishi.github.io/publication/2017jcoph.330..924r/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 01 Feb 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://jsoishi.github.io/publication/2017jcoph.330..924r/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Tensor calculus in polar coordinates using Jacobi polynomials</title>
      <link>https://jsoishi.github.io/publication/2016jcoph.325...53v/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 01 Nov 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://jsoishi.github.io/publication/2016jcoph.325...53v/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Turbulent Chemical Diffusion in Convectively Bounded Carbon Flames</title>
      <link>https://jsoishi.github.io/publication/2016apj...832...71l/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 01 Nov 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://jsoishi.github.io/publication/2016apj...832...71l/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Alex Jiang</title>
      <link>https://jsoishi.github.io/member/xjiang/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 12 Jul 2016 15:52:22 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://jsoishi.github.io/member/xjiang/</guid>
      <description>Alex is working on his senior thesis on the topological properties of torsional oscillations in the Earth&amp;rsquo;s core. He&amp;rsquo;s also worked on Active Matter simulations.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Anthony Okonkwo</title>
      <link>https://jsoishi.github.io/member/aokonkwo/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 12 Jul 2016 15:52:22 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://jsoishi.github.io/member/aokonkwo/</guid>
      <description>Anthony is a senior thesis student working on fluid-structure interactions using immersed boundary methods in Dedalus.
Hobbies </description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Avi Brach-Neufeld</title>
      <link>https://jsoishi.github.io/member/abrachne/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 12 Jul 2016 15:52:22 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://jsoishi.github.io/member/abrachne/</guid>
      <description>Avi is writing his senior thesis on the Goldreich-Schubert-Fricke instability.
Hobbies </description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Becca Minsley</title>
      <link>https://jsoishi.github.io/member/rminsley/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 12 Jul 2016 15:52:22 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://jsoishi.github.io/member/rminsley/</guid>
      <description>Becca is just joining the group. She&amp;rsquo;s going to work with Alex on Active Matter.
Hobbies </description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Deveena Banerjee</title>
      <link>https://jsoishi.github.io/member/dbanerje/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 12 Jul 2016 15:52:22 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://jsoishi.github.io/member/dbanerje/</guid>
      <description>Deveena hails from Sacramento, CA. She&amp;rsquo;s interested in magnetohydrodynamic simulations.
Hobbies </description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Fahim Khan</title>
      <link>https://jsoishi.github.io/member/fkhan/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 12 Jul 2016 15:52:22 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://jsoishi.github.io/member/fkhan/</guid>
      <description>Fahim is developing a dashboard for managing supercomputer simulations.
Hobbies </description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Hannah Beams</title>
      <link>https://jsoishi.github.io/member/hbeams/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 12 Jul 2016 15:52:22 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://jsoishi.github.io/member/hbeams/</guid>
      <description>Hannah is just joining the group. She&amp;rsquo;s starting a project to simulate the KPZ equation in Dedalus.
Hobbies </description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Jeff Oishi</title>
      <link>https://jsoishi.github.io/member/jeff_oishi/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 12 Jul 2016 15:52:22 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://jsoishi.github.io/member/jeff_oishi/</guid>
      <description>Jeff develops numerical algorithms and software to model partial differential equations (PDEs). He uses them to study complicated non-linear flows and turbulence in fluids and plasmas. This involves great students, a lot of coffee, a fair amount of supercomputer time, and a network of great friends and collaborators around the world to work with.
Hobbies Loud music, synthesizers, bicycles, cats.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Kirstin Koepnic</title>
      <link>https://jsoishi.github.io/member/kkoepnic/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 12 Jul 2016 15:52:22 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://jsoishi.github.io/member/kkoepnic/</guid>
      <description>Kirstin wrote her senior thesis on topological protection in fluid systems. She is now a PhD student in Applied Mathematics at Harvard.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Matt Goldberg</title>
      <link>https://jsoishi.github.io/member/mgoldbe2/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 12 Jul 2016 15:52:22 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://jsoishi.github.io/member/mgoldbe2/</guid>
      <description>Matt wrote his senior thesis on the formation of jets on the 2-sphere using a very primative version of what is now Dedalus 3. He is now a PhD student in Computational Science, Engineering, and Mathematics at UT Austin.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Mike Bancroft</title>
      <link>https://jsoishi.github.io/member/mbancroft/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 12 Jul 2016 15:52:22 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://jsoishi.github.io/member/mbancroft/</guid>
      <description>Mike hails from New Hampsire. He&amp;rsquo;s now working at Dartmouth College.
Hobbies skiing</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Morgan Baxter</title>
      <link>https://jsoishi.github.io/member/mbaxter/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 12 Jul 2016 15:52:22 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://jsoishi.github.io/member/mbaxter/</guid>
      <description>Morgan wrote his senior thesis on applying the Generalized Quasi-linear Approximation to Taylor-Couette flows. Before that, Morgan completed an eigenvalue analysis of the 3D magnetorotational instability. As of 2021, he&amp;rsquo;s pursuing a Master&amp;rsquo;s Degree in Aerospace Engineering at University of Colorado, Boulder.
Hobbies </description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Muhammad Abdullah</title>
      <link>https://jsoishi.github.io/member/mabdulla/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 12 Jul 2016 15:52:22 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://jsoishi.github.io/member/mabdulla/</guid>
      <description>Abdullah completed his senior thesis on machine learning methods for finding exact coherent states in plane Couette flow. He also worked on the thermal asymptotic suction boundary layer problem.
He is currently a PhD student in Prof. George Park&amp;rsquo;s group at the University of Pennsylvania Mechanical Engineering and Applied Mechanics department.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Reed Feldman</title>
      <link>https://jsoishi.github.io/member/reed_feldman/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 12 Jul 2016 15:52:22 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://jsoishi.github.io/member/reed_feldman/</guid>
      <description>Reed developed a web framework for managing and creating Dedalus jobs from simulation parameter design documents.
Hobbies </description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Sam Huebschmann</title>
      <link>https://jsoishi.github.io/member/sam_huebschmann/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 12 Jul 2016 15:52:22 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://jsoishi.github.io/member/sam_huebschmann/</guid>
      <description>Sam completed his senior thesis by building a Raspberry pi &amp;ldquo;supercomputer.&amp;rdquo;
Hobbies </description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>A validated non-linear Kelvin-Helmholtz benchmark for numerical hydrodynamics</title>
      <link>https://jsoishi.github.io/publication/2016mnras.455.4274l/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Feb 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://jsoishi.github.io/publication/2016mnras.455.4274l/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Numerical simulations of internal wave generation by convection in water</title>
      <link>https://jsoishi.github.io/publication/2015phrve..91f3016l/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jun 2015 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://jsoishi.github.io/publication/2015phrve..91f3016l/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Self-generated Turbulence in Magnetic Reconnection</title>
      <link>https://jsoishi.github.io/publication/2015apj...806l..12o/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jun 2015 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://jsoishi.github.io/publication/2015apj...806l..12o/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Conduction in Low Mach Number Flows. I. Linear and Weakly Nonlinear Regimes</title>
      <link>https://jsoishi.github.io/publication/2014apj...797...94l/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Dec 2014 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://jsoishi.github.io/publication/2014apj...797...94l/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>ENZO: An Adaptive Mesh Refinement Code for Astrophysics</title>
      <link>https://jsoishi.github.io/publication/2014apjs..211...19b/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 01 Apr 2014 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://jsoishi.github.io/publication/2014apjs..211...19b/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Magnetic Fields in Population III Star Formation</title>
      <link>https://jsoishi.github.io/publication/2012apj...745..154t/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 01 Feb 2012 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://jsoishi.github.io/publication/2012apj...745..154t/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Simulating the Common Envelope Phase of a Red Giant Using Smoothed-particle Hydrodynamics and Uniform-grid Codes</title>
      <link>https://jsoishi.github.io/publication/2012apj...744...52p/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 01 Jan 2012 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://jsoishi.github.io/publication/2012apj...744...52p/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Magnetorotational Turbulence Transports Angular Momentum in Stratified Disks with Low Magnetic Prandtl Number but Magnetic Reynolds Number above a Critical Value</title>
      <link>https://jsoishi.github.io/publication/2011apj...740...18o/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 01 Oct 2011 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://jsoishi.github.io/publication/2011apj...740...18o/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>yt: A Multi-code Analysis Toolkit for Astrophysical Simulation Data</title>
      <link>https://jsoishi.github.io/publication/2011apjs..192....9t/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 01 Jan 2011 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://jsoishi.github.io/publication/2011apjs..192....9t/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>On the Stability of Dust-laden Protoplanetary Vortices</title>
      <link>https://jsoishi.github.io/publication/2010apj...721.1593c/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 01 Oct 2010 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://jsoishi.github.io/publication/2010apj...721.1593c/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>On Hydrodynamic Motions in Dead Zones</title>
      <link>https://jsoishi.github.io/publication/2009apj...704.1239o/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 01 Oct 2009 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://jsoishi.github.io/publication/2009apj...704.1239o/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>A Constrained-Transport Magnetohydrodynamics Algorithm with Near-Spectral Resolution</title>
      <link>https://jsoishi.github.io/publication/2008apj...677..520m/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 01 Apr 2008 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://jsoishi.github.io/publication/2008apj...677..520m/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Turbulent Torques on Protoplanets in a Dead Zone</title>
      <link>https://jsoishi.github.io/publication/2007apj...670..805o/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 01 Nov 2007 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://jsoishi.github.io/publication/2007apj...670..805o/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Dynamical Expansion of H II Regions from Ultracompact to Compact Sizes in Turbulent, Self-gravitating Molecular Clouds</title>
      <link>https://jsoishi.github.io/publication/2007apj...668..980m/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Oct 2007 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://jsoishi.github.io/publication/2007apj...668..980m/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Rapid planetesimal formation in turbulent circumstellar disks</title>
      <link>https://jsoishi.github.io/publication/2007natur.448.1022j/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 01 Aug 2007 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://jsoishi.github.io/publication/2007natur.448.1022j/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The Inability of Ambipolar Diffusion to Set a Characteristic Mass Scale in Molecular Clouds</title>
      <link>https://jsoishi.github.io/publication/2006apj...638..281o/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 01 Feb 2006 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://jsoishi.github.io/publication/2006apj...638..281o/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Cassiopeia A and Its Clumpy Presupernova Wind</title>
      <link>https://jsoishi.github.io/publication/2003apj...593l..23c/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 01 Aug 2003 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://jsoishi.github.io/publication/2003apj...593l..23c/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title></title>
      <link>https://jsoishi.github.io/vacancy/vacancy1/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://jsoishi.github.io/vacancy/vacancy1/</guid>
      <description>Joining the group If you&amp;rsquo;re an undergrad at Bates&amp;ndash;any year, physics major, potential physics major, or otherwise&amp;ndash;send email to Jeff. Browse around the site to get a feel for what we&amp;rsquo;re up to. There are no prerequisites to joining the group; interest in some subset of {math, physics, programming} is pretty much it. If you&amp;rsquo;re even a little curious about it, send me an email and let&amp;rsquo;s chat.
Doing a Senior Thesis Are you a physics major thinking of doing a senior thesis?</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>