<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Researches on Bates Fluid Dynamics Group</title>
    <link>https://jsoishi.github.io/research/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Researches on Bates Fluid Dynamics Group</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <copyright>&amp;copy; Jeffrey S. Oishi, 2018-present; banner image NASA/SWRI/MSSS/Gerald Eichstädt/Seán Doran</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Wed, 17 Jul 2019 08:50:58 +0200</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="https://jsoishi.github.io/research/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Dedalus Tutorials</title>
      <link>https://jsoishi.github.io/research/dedalus_tutorials/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 17 Jul 2019 08:50:58 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://jsoishi.github.io/research/dedalus_tutorials/</guid>
      <description>Double Diffusive Convection In order to run this, you can find the code at Github.
First, we have the so-called &amp;ldquo;fingering&amp;rdquo; regime of DDC, which you can run with this script   
Next, we have &amp;ldquo;overstable&amp;rdquo; DDC, which you can run with this script</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Guide to Getting Started </title>
      <link>https://jsoishi.github.io/research/getting_started/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 22 Nov 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://jsoishi.github.io/research/getting_started/</guid>
      <description>Welcome to the Bates Fluid Dynamics Group! Most of our work involves solving partial differential equations by computer. Typically, this means running simulations on supercomputers, most often the Leavitt cluster here at Bates.
Using Linux  All of the group&amp;rsquo;s software runs on Linux. You need to be familiar with the command line, and it helps to know a bit of bash shell scripting. We use the git version control system.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Using Leavitt</title>
      <link>https://jsoishi.github.io/research/leavitt/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 22 Nov 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://jsoishi.github.io/research/leavitt/</guid>
      <description>Basics When you log in to leavitt via ssh, you will be on the &amp;ldquo;head node&amp;rdquo;. This node is identical to the other nodes. It has 28 cores and 128 GB of memory. This machine is for doing small analysis tasks and submitting jobs. DO NOT RUN DEDALUS ON THE HEAD NODE. Instead, use a job script to submit runs to the compute nodes.
Modules System Leavitt uses modules to manage various software packages.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Research Overview</title>
      <link>https://jsoishi.github.io/research/overview/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 19 Jul 2018 08:50:58 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://jsoishi.github.io/research/overview/</guid>
      <description>Mission The Bates Fluid Dynamics Group study fluid dynamics at scales ranging from global models of planets and stars to the swimming and growth of bacteria with theoretical and computational tools. We are particularly interested in what we call &amp;ldquo;complicated&amp;rdquo; fluid dynamics: problems involving turbulence, phase changes, traditional &amp;ldquo;complex&amp;rdquo; non-Newtonian fluids, or some combination of them all. We make extensive use of the Dedalus Project, a flexible framework for solving partial differential equations.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>