<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Posts on Bates Fluid Dynamics Group</title>
    <link>https://jsoishi.github.io/post/index.xml</link>
    <description>Recent content in Posts on Bates Fluid Dynamics Group</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <copyright>&amp;copy; Jeffrey S. Oishi, 2018; banner image NASA/SWRI/MSSS/Gerald Eichstädt/Seán Doran</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Sat, 14 Sep 2019 15:01:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="https://jsoishi.github.io/post/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    <item>
      <title>Papers published!</title>
      <link>https://jsoishi.github.io/post/spheres-papers/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 14 Sep 2019 15:01:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://jsoishi.github.io/post/spheres-papers/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;m excited to annouce that our two papers on spin-weighted spherical harmonics are finally published in the Journal of Computational Physics X. The &lt;a href=&#34;https://doi.org/10.1016/j.jcpx.2019.100013&#34;&gt;first paper&lt;/a&gt; covers the mathematical formalism, while the &lt;a href=&#34;https://doi.org/10.1016/j.jcpx.2019.100012&#34;&gt;second paper&lt;/a&gt; demonstrates its performance in a number of test problems, including a fully convective, rotating dynamo problem:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://jsoishi.github.io/img/1-s2.0-S2590055219300289-gr010.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;spherical dynamo&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On the right is the radial velocity while the left shows magnetic field lines, visualized using Vapor.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The most significant part of this research, aside from the fact that we have sparse, efficient spectrally accurate spherical basis functions in Dedalus, is that by using spin-weighted spherical harmonics, one can implement equations on the sphere directly in vector form:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://jsoishi.github.io/img/2019-09-29-204108_1325x457_scrot.png&#34; alt=&#34;equations&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Previously, one would have to write equations in poloidal-toridal form in order to expand them in spherical harmonics. By constructing spectrally accurate solutions for vector partial differential equations on the sphere, we can now get ready for a lot of exciting research on the sphere!&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Welcome back!</title>
      <link>https://jsoishi.github.io/post/new-year-2019-2020/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 14 Sep 2019 15:01:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://jsoishi.github.io/post/new-year-2019-2020/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;It&amp;rsquo;s the start of a new year, and we have several new members in the group. Welcome to senior thesis students Fahim Khan and Avi Brach-Neufeld, juniors Hannah Beams, Becca Minsley, and Alex Jiang! Morgan Baxter is returning from a successful summer project to start his senior thesis as well.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Fahim is going to be focusing on some interesting infrastructure, trying to figure out how to streamline the management of supercomputer simulations. Avi will be investiating the non-linear Goldreich-Schubert-Fricke instability. Morgan Baxter will be continuing on to applying GQL to &lt;a href=&#34;https://dedalus-project.readthedocs.io/en/latest/notebooks/TaylorCouetteFlow.html&#34;&gt;Taylor-Couette flows&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Becca and Alex are starting a new project to find exact non-linear states for &lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Active_matter&#34;&gt;active matter&lt;/a&gt;. Meanwhile, Hannah is going to lead the charge to apply Dedalus to stochastic PDEs, with an investigation of the &lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Kardar%E2%80%93Parisi%E2%80%93Zhang_equation&#34;&gt;KPZ equation&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It was a busy and productive summer, with Morgan&amp;rsquo;s summer research project on the magnetorotational instability leading to his first paper, which will be submitted this week. Look for more details very soon.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>GQL Busse Annulus paper published</title>
      <link>https://jsoishi.github.io/post/gql-busse-paper/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 05 Dec 2018 17:23:48 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://jsoishi.github.io/post/gql-busse-paper/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://royalsocietypublishing.org/doi/10.1098/rspa.2018.0422&#34;&gt;Our paper&lt;/a&gt; on the Generalized Quasi-linear Approximation for the Busse Annulus problem was published in Proceedings of the Royal Society A!&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>New website!</title>
      <link>https://jsoishi.github.io/post/post1/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 05 Nov 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://jsoishi.github.io/post/post1/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;So we built a website!&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>