<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Projects on Bates Fluid Dynamics Group</title>
    <link>https://jsoishi.github.io/project/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Projects on Bates Fluid Dynamics Group</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <copyright>&amp;copy; Jeffrey S. Oishi, 2018; banner image NASA/SWRI/MSSS/Gerald Eichstädt/Seán Doran</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Mon, 01 Oct 2018 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="https://jsoishi.github.io/project/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>A Complex Fluids Toolkit for Dedalus</title>
      <link>https://jsoishi.github.io/project/complex_fluids_toolkit/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Oct 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://jsoishi.github.io/project/complex_fluids_toolkit/</guid>
      <description>Motivation Complex fluids, including liquid crystals and those with non-Newtonian rheologies, are extremely important in a wide variety of disciplines, from biological to industrial. We are developing a series of tools to extend the Dedalus to include multiphase flows with varying rheologies.
Methods We make extensive use of the phase field method to simulate two fluids on the same grid. This idea, sometimes also called the &amp;ldquo;diffusive interface model&amp;rdquo;, assumes that we resolve the interface between the two fluids.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Direct Statistical Simulation for unsteady flows</title>
      <link>https://jsoishi.github.io/project/busseannulus/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 01 May 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://jsoishi.github.io/project/busseannulus/</guid>
      <description>Motivation Direct Statistical Simulation is a relatively new and very promising technique for understanding the long-term statistical properties of highly turbulent, anisotropic flow. Anisotropic flow occurs in astrophysical and geophysical contexts in a number of guises: the zonal jets found on Jupiter and Saturn, the mean dynamo-generated magnetic fields on solar-type and fully convective M-dwarfs, and the quasi-biennial oscillation on Earth. DSS has been extensively verified and tested against many problems in atmospheric science \citep{2008JAtS&amp;hellip;65.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Barotropic Jet Formation on the 2-Sphere using Spin Spherical Harmonics</title>
      <link>https://jsoishi.github.io/project/barotropicjets/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 29 Oct 2017 16:10:22 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://jsoishi.github.io/project/barotropicjets/</guid>
      <description>Motivation The Dedalus Collaboration has developed a sparse discretization of vector fields in spherical geometry. Key to this process is the understanding that vector components, as opposed to scalars, do not have the same regularities as the standard spherical harmonics. However, by using a basis that does have the right regularity, we can construct a sparse matrix solution to differential equations in curvilinear geometries. This basis is the spin-weighted spherical harmonics, constructed from Jacobi polynomials.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Magnetohydrodynamics on the Equatorial Beta Plane</title>
      <link>https://jsoishi.github.io/project/mhdbetaplane/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 12 Jul 2016 16:10:22 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://jsoishi.github.io/project/mhdbetaplane/</guid>
      <description>Motivation Motivated by the discovery of active nests of convection in rapidly rotating stellar simulations, we are interested in constructing a local model that can reproduce the phenomena. In order to do this, we&amp;rsquo;re investigating the use of the equatorial beta plane.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>