<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Projects on Bates Fluid Dynamics Group</title>
    <link>https://jsoishi.github.io/project/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Projects on Bates Fluid Dynamics Group</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <copyright>&amp;copy; Jeffrey S. Oishi, 2018-present; banner image NASA/SWRI/MSSS/Gerald Eichstädt/Seán Doran</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Sat, 01 Jul 2023 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="https://jsoishi.github.io/project/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Minimal Models of Moist Convection</title>
      <link>https://jsoishi.github.io/project/moistconvection/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 01 Jul 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://jsoishi.github.io/project/moistconvection/</guid>
      <description>Motivation When water vapor condenses in the atmosphere, it releases latent heat and changes the buoyancy of the surrounding air. This phase transition is a fundamentally non-linear process that dramatically shapes the evolution of convection, making it fundamentally different than ``dry&amp;rsquo;&amp;rsquo; convection without moisture. Convective activity plays a key role in the climate system, including the radiation inhibition driven by clouds and the formation of severe weather. Today&amp;rsquo;s most advanced global climate models do not reliably resolve the formation of clouds, and thus they include significant model-dependent details that drive disagreements in the results.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Reduced Models: GQL, DSS, and anisotropic flows</title>
      <link>https://jsoishi.github.io/project/reducedmodels/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 01 Dec 2020 16:10:22 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://jsoishi.github.io/project/reducedmodels/</guid>
      <description>Turbulence is a crucial part of the climate, the dynamo process by which the Sun and Earth produce magnetic fields, and a major limiting factor for plasma confinement in tokamaks. In each of these systems, the largest scales are factors of 105 to 1014 times larger than the smallest scales. Crucially, energy flows through all of these scales, impacting the dynamics of the flow. A complete numerical simulation would require between 1015 to 1042 data points for every moment in time simulated!</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>A Complex Fluids Toolkit for Dedalus</title>
      <link>https://jsoishi.github.io/project/complex_fluids_toolkit/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Oct 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://jsoishi.github.io/project/complex_fluids_toolkit/</guid>
      <description>Motivation Complex fluids, including liquid crystals and those with non-Newtonian rheologies, are extremely important in a wide variety of disciplines, from biological to industrial. We are developing a series of tools to extend the Dedalus to include multiphase flows with varying rheologies.
Methods We make extensive use of the phase field method to simulate two fluids on the same grid. This idea, sometimes also called the &amp;ldquo;diffusive interface model&amp;rdquo;, assumes that we resolve the interface between the two fluids.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Direct Statistical Simulation for unsteady flows</title>
      <link>https://jsoishi.github.io/project/busseannulus/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 01 May 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://jsoishi.github.io/project/busseannulus/</guid>
      <description>Motivation Direct Statistical Simulation is a relatively new and very promising technique for understanding the long-term statistical properties of highly turbulent, anisotropic flow. Anisotropic flow occurs in astrophysical and geophysical contexts in a number of guises: the zonal jets found on Jupiter and Saturn, the mean dynamo-generated magnetic fields on solar-type and fully convective M-dwarfs, and the quasi-biennial oscillation on Earth. DSS has been extensively verified and tested against many problems in atmospheric science \citep{2008JAtS&amp;hellip;65.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>